{"tossups": [{"question": "This thinker led the prosecution in the impeachment trial of Warren Hastings. He ended his friendship with his prot\u00e9g\u00e9 Charles James Fox after declaring his support for William Pitt the Younger. This man wrote the first major text to separate the categories of the \u201cbeautiful\u201d and the  \u201csublime\u201d and attacked the \u201cabstract\u201d grounds for a certain political upheaval in his major work. For the point, name this father of modern English conservatism, a Whig who wrote <em>Reflections</em> <em>on the Revolution in France</em>.", "answer": "Edmund <b><u>Burke</u> </b> [Rob Carson]", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "In 1950, this team signed Sweetwater Clifton, one of the NBA\u2019s first African-American players. Under coach Red Holzman, this team won their first championship after Willis Reed played through a leg injury in Game 7 of the Finals. In the 1990s, this team had rivalries with the Heat and Pacers and lost in the 1994 and 1999 NBA Finals. This team recently released Amare Stoudemire, though they are still led by Carmelo Anthony. For the point, name this basketball team that plays home games at Madison Square Garden.", "answer": "<b><u>New York</u><u>Knicks</u></b> [accept either underlined portion] [Tejas Raje]", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "A member of this political party, Timothy Pickering, ran a political machine called the Essex Junto. Members of this party wore black cockades in their hats, and at one point were accused of  treason for using \u201cblue lights\u201d to guide enemy warships. This party collapsed after some of its members organized the Hartford Convention.It never won a presidential election after being defeated by Thomas Jefferson. For the point, name this early political party of John Adams and George Washington.", "answer": "<b><u>Federalist</u></b> Party  [Bruce Arth<u>ur]</u>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This country was home to the Communist MRTA movement and the Maoist Shining Path. This nation became independent following the defeat of royalist forces under Jose de la Serna at the battles of Jun\u00edn and Ayacucho. An empire in this country crumbled following the massacre at Cajamarca. It was once ruled by sapas such as Tupac Amaru and Atahualpa. For the point, the heartland of the Inca Empire was in what country whose modern-day capital is Lima?", "answer": "<b><u>Peru</u> </b> [Zihan Zhen<u>g]</u>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "The measured distance to this object was doubled upon Walter Baade\u2019s discovery of Type II Cepheid variables in this object. The Triangulum is theorized to be a satellite of this object. Edwin Hubble used this object to settle the Shapley-Curtis Debate over the size of the universe. This object is designated 224 in the New General Catalogue and 31 in the Messier catalogue, and is the largest galaxy in the Local Group. For the point, name this galaxy, the closest spiral galaxy to the Milky Way.", "answer": "<b><u>Andromeda</u></b> Galaxy [or <b><u>NGC 224</u></b> until \u201c224\u201d is read; or <b><u>M31</u></b> until \u201c31\u201d is read]", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Astronomy"}, {"question": "A dark version of this product common in Finnish communities is called Limppu. A type of  this substance that uses teff is common in Ethiopia and is called Injera. It\u2019s not chicken, but another version may contain yogurt, is often cooked in a tandoori oven, and is called Naan. This product was enriched with vitamins, sliced, and sold in American supermarkets with the  adjective \u201cWonder.\u201d For the point, name this foodstuff that can come in pumpernickel, rye, or sourdough varieties.", "answer": "<b><u>bread</u></b>s  [Dan Passne<u>r]</u>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "During this war, members of the St. Patrick\u2019s Battalion was executed for treason. Near the end  of this war, cadets known as the \u201chero children\u201d were killed defending Grasshopper Hill.  Tennessee earned the nickname \u201cVolunteer State\u201d during this war, in which the enemy capital was captured by Winfield Scott. This war began when US forces crossed the Nueces River and ended in the Treaty of Guadalupe Hidalgo. For the point, name this war where the United States fought its southern neighbor.", "answer": "<b><u>Mexican-American</u></b> War  [Bruce Arth<u>ur]</u>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "During an unsuccessful assassination attempt on this president, Leslie Coffelt killed and was killed by Griselio Torresola, a Puerto Rican nationalist. While swearing this man in, Harlan Stone said the wrong middle name, possibly because this man\u2019s middle name was a single letter.  Youngstown Sheet & Tube Co v. Sawyer reversed this president\u2019s seizure of the steel mills during the Korean War. For 10 points, name this president whose decision to drop atomic bombs on Japan ended WWII.", "answer": "Harry S. <b><u>Truman</u> </b> [Victor Prieto]", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Prior to one of these events, the second husband of Licinia Eudoxia was stoned to death by an angry mob. One of these occurred after troops entered the Salarian Gates and resulted in the destruction of the Gardens of Sallust. Gaiseric perpetrated one of these events that destroyed the Temple of Jupiter Optimus Maximus and was the origin of the term \"vandalism.\" For the point, name these events, which resulted in the eventual downfall of a certain empire around 476 CE.", "answer": "<b><u>sack</u></b>s of <b><u>Rome</u> </b> [Chris Man<u>ners]</u>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "This caliphate's princes sponsored the building of Mshatta and Qusayr Amra. This dynasty sponsored a building with a notable mosaic cycle of landscapes. The Dome of the Rock was built by this dynasty's ruler Abd-al-Malik. This dynasty came to power after Hasan signed a treaty with Muwaiyah I. This dynasty was overthrown by Abu Muslim. For the point, name this dynasty overthrown by the Abbasids whose capital was in Damascus.", "answer": "<b><u>Umayyad</u></b> caliphate  [Doug Grae<u>bner]</u>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Husband Kimmel and Walter Short were essentially fired for being unprepared for this event. A famous picture taken during this event depicts the explosion of the <em>U.S.S. Trent</em>, although the greatest loss of life was aboard the <em>U.S.S. Arizona</em>. Shortly after this event, a speech labeled the day of this event \"a date which will live in infamy.\" For 10 points, identify this event which forced the United States into World War II after the Japanese bombed a naval base on Oahu, Hawaii.", "answer": "attack on <b><u>Pearl Harbor</u></b> [or any answer describing a Japanese surprise attack on <b><u>Pearl Harbor</u></b> at the s<u>tart of World</u> War II]  <u>[Victor Prieto]</u>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Left-wing opposition to the formation of this government was led by its namesake 80. During the Vel D'hiv roundup, it held thousands in the Winter Velodrome and sent them to an  internment camp at Drancy. Joseph Darnand headed its paramilitary force, the Milice, and this  government\u2019s motto was \"Work, Family, Fatherland\" under Marshal P\u00e9tain. For the point, name this government led by Pierre Laval from a former spa town, a French Nazi puppet state.", "answer": "<b><u>Vichy France</u></b> [prompt on <b><u>France</u></b> before mention]  [Aseem Ke<u>yal]</u>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "The Gulbarg Society Massacre targeted members of this religion. Members of this religion were attacked by the 969 Movement in the Rakhine State Riots. The majority of the Rohingya in Myanmar follow this religion. Members of the BJP were accused of promoting riots targeting members of this religion in Gujarat. For the point, name this religion that is followed by a minority of the population in Myanmar and India and the majority of Indonesians.", "answer": "<b><u>Islam</u></b> [accept word forms like <b><u>Muslim</u></b>s]", "metadata": "Puma"}, {"question": "A painting by this man contains a row of long spears above a large horse\u2019s rear end on the right side, while in the foreground a large key is handed to Ambrogio Spinola by Justin of Nassau. He painted an oil portrait of the Moorish slave Juan de Pareja as a study for his official portrait of Pope Innocent X. This painter of <em>The Surrender of Breda</em> served as the court painter to Philip IV, during which time he included himself in a portrait of the Infanta Margarita Teresa and her entourage. For the point, name this Spanish painter of <em>Las Meninas</em>.", "answer": "Diego <b><u>Velazquez</u></b> [or Diego Rodriguez de Silva y <b><u>Velazquez</u></b>] [Rob Carson]", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "Supporters of this president called themselves \u201cSilver-Grays\u201d. Early in his career, he narrowly lost a gubernatorial election to Silas Wright, before becoming the first popularly-elected Comptroller in the history of New York. This president was opposed for re-nomination by his own Secretary of State, Daniel Webster. He lost northern support by signing the Fugitive Slave Act as part of the Compromise of 1850. For the point, name this last Whig president, who succeeded Zachary Taylor.", "answer": "Millard <b><u>Fillmore</u> </b> [Bruce Arthur]", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "As president, this man signed an expansion of Medicare for prescription drugs into law,  known as Part D. This man\u2019s first attorney general was appointed after losing a Senate election to a dead opponent in Missouri. He appointed the first Hispanic Attorney General and the first black female Secretary of State, Alberto Gonzales and Condoleezza Rice. For the point, name this US President who succeeded Bill Clinton.", "answer": "George <b><u>W</u></b>alker<b><u> Bush</u></b> [accept \u201c<b><u>Dubya</u></b>\u201d; prompt on \u201cBush\u201d or \u201cGeorge Bush\u201d] [Bruce Arthur]", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This number is in the exponent of Gelfond\u2019s constant. The solution to the Basel problem is this number squared over six. The Chudnovsky Brothers developed the supercomputer m-zero to calculate this number using an algorithm based on one by Srinivasa Ramanujan. Johann Lambert proved that this number is irrational using the continued fraction expansion of the tangent  function. For the point, name this ratio of a circle\u2019s circumference to its diameter.", "answer": "<b><u>pi</u> </b> [Sean McBr<u>id</u>e]", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Math"}, {"question": "In one of this director\u2019s films, a man is killed during a production of <em>Cavalleria Rusticana</em>.  The title character of one of this man\u2019s films dies while chasing his grandson through a garden with an orange slice in his mouth. The production of one film by this director was the subject of the documentary <em>Hearts of Darkness</em>. In another of his films, The Turk and Captain McCluskey are killed in Louis Restaurant by Michael Corleone. For the point, name this director of <em>Apocalypse Now</em> and <em>The Godfather</em> trilogy.", "answer": "Francis Ford <b><u>Coppola</u> </b> [Sean McBride]", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Film"}, {"question": "This dynasty is sometimes named for Lagus, the father of its first ruler. The first ruler of this dynasty took the body of Alexander the Great and founded the Serapis cult. Another ruler of this dynasty ordered the execution of Pompey after the Battle of Philippi. This dynasty\u2019s capital was Alexandria. For the point, name this Hellenistic dynasty that ruled Egypt and had many queens named Cleopatra.", "answer": "<b><u>Ptolemaic</u></b> kingdom [or <em><b><u>Ptolemaioi</u></b></em><b><u>;</u></b> or the <b><u>Ptolemies</u></b>] [Patrick Lia<u>o]</u>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "This man presented a \u201cdoctrine of the international community\u201d to justify intervention in  Kosovo on humanitarian grounds. This leader revised Clause IV of his party\u2019s constitution to create the \u201cNew\u201d version of that party. Negotiations between Bertie Ahern and this man produced the Good Friday Agreement. He was succeeded by his Chancellor of the Exchequer, Gordon Brown. For the point, name this UK Prime Minister from 1997-2007.", "answer": "Tony <b><u>Blair</u> </b> [Ryan Rosenberg<u>]</u>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "This man\u2019s third opera is based on the life of a medieval Italian populist leader who was known as the \u201clast of the tribunes\u201d. This composer of <em>Rienzi</em> took part in the May Uprising in Dresden and wrote a polemic attacking Meyerbeer and Mendelssohn called <em>Judaism in Music</em>. He had an opera house built in Bayreuth at which his most famous works, including <em>Parsifal</em>, were premiered. For the point, name this composer of <em>The Flying Dutchman</em> who included the \u201cRide of the Valkyries\u201d in his <em>Ring Cycle</em>.", "answer": "Richard <b><u>Wagner</u></b> [or Wilhelm Richard <b><u>Wagner</u></b>]  [Rob Carson]", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "In Zoroastrianism, this event involves the appearance of the Saoshyant and is called Frashokereti. In Islam it is comprised of the Yawm al-Qiyamah and Yawm al-din and includes a battle between Isa and Masih al-Dajjal. Some Christians believe it includes the Battle of Gog and Magog and the appearance of the Whore of Babylon. This concept is the general subject of the field of eschatology. For the point, identify this event which, according to Christianity, may include a rapture and is described in Revelation.", "answer": "the <b><u>end of the world</u></b> [accept equivalents like <b><u>Armageddon</u></b>, the <b><u>end of time</u></b>, the <b><u>end of days</u></b>, th<u>e</u> <b><u>cleansing of th</u><u>e world</u></b>, the <b><u>end times</u></b>, t<u>he</u> <b><u>renovation</u><u> of t</u><u>he universe</u></b><u>,</u> or other <u>obvious syn</u>onym<u>s indicating the end or</u> rema<u>king of th</u>ings i<u>n general]</u>  [Dan Pa]", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "An equestrian statue of this man sits atop the Thunder Stone, the largest monolith ever quarried and moved by humans. This man officially founded his country's navy after capturing the port of Azov. Early in his reign, this man spent 18 months traveling incognito across Europe. When he returned, he imposed a tax on beards to promote Westernization. This man vanquished his foe Charles XII at Poltava, a victory that helped his country win the Great Northern War. For the point, name this Tsar of Russia who founded St. Petersburg.", "answer": "<b><u>Peter the Great</u></b> [Also accept: <b><u>Peter I]</u> </b> [Blake N<u>eff]</u>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "When preceded by \u201cNational\u201d, this names a short-lived political party led by Henry Clay and John Quincy Adams. When preceded by \u201cLiberal\u201d, this word names a splinter party that nominated Horace Greeley for president. Most commonly, this word names a party founded in Ripon, Wisconsin. Ben Wade, Thaddeus Stevens, and Charles Sumner adopted tough stances on reconstruction that made them \u201cradical\u201d members of this party. For the point, name this American political party, the rivals of the Democrats.", "answer": "<b><u>Republican</u></b> Party [or <b><u>Grand Old Party</u></b>; or <b><u>GOP</u></b>]  [Bruce Arth<u>ur]</u>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "One of this nation\u2019s colonies gained independence under the leadership of Samora Machel.  The Alvor Agreement ended another conflict between this nation and its former colony of  Angola. Operation Vijay succeeded in conquering one of this nation\u2019s overseas territories, the exclave of Goa, and this country gave up its colonies after the failure of the Estado Novo. For the point, name this European country once ruled by Antonio Salazar.", "answer": "<b><u>Portugal</u> </b> [Vasa Clark<u>e]</u>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "One of these weapons was sabotaged with a torpedo in a daring raid led by William Cushing. At the Battle of Drewry\u2019s Bluff, one of these weapons was unable to elevate its guns and engage the enemy. An early one of these weapons sank the <em>Cumberland</em> and <em>Congress</em> before fighting another of these weapons to a stalemate at the Battle of Hampton Roads. For the point, name these Civil War-era warships, example of which included the CSS <em>Virginia</em> and USS <em>Monitor</em>.", "answer": "<b><u>ironclad</u></b>s [accept ironclad <b><u>ram</u></b>s before \u201celevate\u201d]  [Vasa Clark<u>e]</u>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man became heir to the throne in the Treaty of Winchester. To punish him for an affair with Rosamund Clifford, his wife encouraged his three oldest sons to rebel against him along  with Louis VII of France. After this king loudly complained about a \u201cmeddlesome priest,\u201d four knights went to Canterbury Cathedral and murdered Thomas Becket. For the point, name this king of England, the father of John and Richard the Lionheart and husband of Eleanor of Aquitaine.", "answer": "<b><u>Henry II</u> </b> [Tejas Raje]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "After becoming a republican through his friendship with Baron Severino Cassio, this man fell out of political favor when he refused to wear a page uniform to serve the son of Charles Felix. This politician briefly resigned after the Peace of Villafranca, but returned and gave up Nice and Savoy to retain French support, which had been secured by the 1858 Treaty of Plombieres. For the point, name this Piedmontese statesman and first Prime Minister of a unified Italy.", "answer": "Camillo Paolo Filippo Giulio <b><u>Benso</u></b>, count di <b><u>Cavour</u></b> [accept either underlined portion]  [Patrick Liao]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "These people celebrate the first laughs of their babies, on the belief that the action signals detachment from the spirit world. Their mythos includes the figures of the Spider Woman and Spider Man, whose weavings lead these people to craft wedding baskets. European influence led  to materials such as indigo being used in this people\u2019s blankets and rugs. For the point, hogans are the traditional dwellings of what southwestern Native Americans, whose complex language  was used by World War II \u201cWindtalkers\u201d?", "answer": "<b><u>Navajo</u></b> [or <b><u>Dine</u></b>]  [Dan Pa]", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}], "bonuses": []}